Guide to the American Studies Seminars in Japan Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
American Studies Seminars in Japan records
1950-1981
1950-1960
SC0266
Stanford University
2.25 Linear feet (5 boxes)
The records consist mostly of correspondence but also include memoranda, reports, financial documents, syllabi, bibliographies, clippings, and several photograph albums. Some of the materials relate to seminars held in Kyoto, 1951-1952. There is one file on establishing an American Studies Program at Stanford, 1953. Collection includes extensive correspondence of Hideo Kishimoto, 1952-1960, with some typescript articles and talks. Other correspondents include Claude Buss, John D. Goheen, J. E. Wallace Sterling, George H. Knoles, George H. Kerr, Shinzo Kaji, Morton G. White, and Perry Miller.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The records were received by the Stanford University Archives via administrative transfer in 1980.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The American Studies Seminars in Japan were jointly sponsored by Stanford and the University of Tokyo and partially funded by the Ford Foundation. The seminars, held in the summers of 1950 to 1956, were taught by American scholars in various fields for students at the University of Tokyo. Among the seminar organizers were Hideo Kishimoto and Shinzo Kaji of the University of Tokyo and George Harmon Knoles and John D. Goheen of Stanford.
Description of the Collection
The records consist mostly of correspondence but also include memoranda, reports, financial documents, syllabi, bibliographies, clippings, and several photograph albums. Some of the materials relate to seminars held in Kyoto, 1951-1952. There is one file on establishing an American Studies Program at Stanford, 1953. Collection includes extensive correspondence of Hideo Kishimoto, 1952-1960, with some typescript articles and talks. Other correspondents include Claude Buss, John D. Goheen, J. E. Wallace Sterling, George H. Knoles, George H. Kerr, Shinzo Kaji, Morton G. White, and Perry Miller. The collection also includes the Bulletin of the Center for American Studies of the University of Tokyo, Nov. 4, 1981, with recollections of the seminars by its participants.
Access Terms
Buss, Claude Albert.; Goheen, John D.; Kaji, Shinzo.; Kerr, George H., 1911-; Kishimoto, Hideo, 1903-1964.; Knoles, George Harmon.; Miller, Perry, 1905-1963.; Stanford University; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; White, Morton Gabriel, 1917-; Intercultural education.; Photoprints.; United States--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Records, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Records, class materials, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Records, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Records, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Records, clippings of lectures from the Seminars from newspaper The Manichi, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Records, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Records, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- American Studies Degree at Stanford, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Records, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Records, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Notes from John Goheen's Trip, 1955 Jun (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Budget, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Records, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Miscellaneous, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- American Studies Seminars Addenda (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Staff (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Book orders (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Institute for American Studies at the University of Tokyo, memoranda on, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rockefeller Foundation, 1952-1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Rockefeller Foundation, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- American Studies Seminar in Kyoto, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- American Studies Seminar in Kyoto, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1952-53 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Hideo Kishimoto correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Bulletin of the Center for American Studies of the University of Tokyo, No. 4, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Photo albums (3): opening ceremonies, seminars, professors, group photographs, parties, 1950-1952 (Box 4)
- Photo album: opening session, seminars, professors, group photographs, social activities, 1956 (Box 5)